foreign
[Music]
there are numerous ways to try to unlock
the mysteries of Aging you could study
long-lived individuals like centenarians
and super centenarians a particularly
long-lived smokers perhaps to uncover
the secrets to their resilience or you
could go in the opposite direction and
study short-lived people tragic
accelerated aging syndromes like
Progeria or children age at eight to ten
times the normal rate wrinkling balding
and then typically dying around age 13
of a heart attack or stroke or you could
study long-lived animals there are
mammals such as a bowhead whale that can
live hundreds of years there are oysters
and clams whose Hearts can be over a
billion times over its five Century
lifespan what accounts for the 10 000
fold range of lifespan in the animal
kingdom
most of the Aging Pathways identified as
the Hallmarks of Aging were established
using so-called model organisms such as
yeast worms flies and mice simpler
species that may nonetheless offer
insights due to the remarkable
conservation of common aging mechanisms
through the eons of evolutionary time
aging used to be considered simply too
complex to study a constellation of
internal and external influences too
complicated to disentangle but then the
game changer the discovery that a single
gene mutation could dramatically prolong
the lifespan and Youthful state of a
tiny worm known as C elegans
see elegans since wormed its way deep
into the study of longevity it seems we
shared a common ancestor about a half
billion years ago and to this day we
still share about half their genes or
with a lifespan of only two to three
weeks their fast turnover allows
researchers to rapidly assess the
effects of genetic or dietary tweaks
unlike humans who are described as not
an easy to study system both for ethical
as well as for practical reasons even
simpler the single-celled organisms
saccharomyces cervasia otherwise known
as Brewers or baker's yeast in 1959 it
was discovered that yeast cells are not
Immortal dividing only a finite number
of times they are even more
evolutionarily Divergent though we
haven't shared a common ancestor with
brewers yeast for more than a billion
years
and only have about 30 of their genes in
common at this point but their
microscopic size and even faster
turnover allows for high throughput
systems able to Screen through more than
a thousand different compounds a day for
potentially lifespan extending
properties
and even if those yeast longevity
compounds fail to translate to extending
human life yeast researchers argue they
could still be useful for Brewing Extra
beer
yeast have a lifespan that can be
measured in days worms and weeks fruit
flies another common model in months
compared to mice that can live for years
but Mice and Men were one as few as 75
million years ago arising in the
mammalian explosion short after the
resolution of the asteroid V dinosaurs
matchup
mice share about 85 percent of their
genes with humans granted it's an
important 15 percent
humans are not just more complex
anatomically than rodents but more
complex even on a cellular level
extrapolating data from lab animals is
infamously fraught with difficulty fewer
than one in ten Cancer drugs that seem
to work in mice even make it into human
clinical trials and hundreds of
seemingly promising Alzheimer's drugs
have similarly been lost in translation
as one review in the journal Trends in
biotechnology put it humans are not huge
worms or big mice we are however big
primates rhesus monkeys are also used in
aging research though can live up to 40
years stretching research timelines
their DNA is 93 percent identical to
humans though a similarity increases so
too do ethical concerns regarding
experimentation one might expect
research on dogs perhaps be most
sensitive but there are citizen science
initiatives in which family dogs are
enrolled in non-invasive studies to
study for example the genetics of why
some so-called Methuselah dogs reach
ages of 25 or more but 99.9 of other
dogs do not for example mixed breed dogs
live more than a year longer than the
same sized purebred dogs who can be
plagued with certain genetic disorders
aged pooches suffer many of the same
ravages of Aging arthritis cancer
cataracts kidney problems muscle loss
Etc advances in canine longevity might
not only be applicable to human aging
but have the intrinsic value of
enhancing the quality and quantity of
life of the more than 70 million
companions we share our homes with in
the us alone
foreign